[Music]
start with a square of side length y
covering an area of y squared
then remove a square from the lower left
corner with side length z so that the
resulting area is y squared minus z
squared
we can cut the resulting nomen in half
along the diagonal creating two
trapezoids
move one of the trapezoids down
rotate it
and then flip it to connect it to the
other trapezoid resulting in a rectangle
the rectangle has side length y minus z
and the other side length is y plus z
therefore the original area of y squared
minus z squared is the same as the
product of y plus z
and y minus z
this formula is known as the difference
of squares formula
we can plug in x plus a over 2 for y and
a over 2 for z so that y plus z is x
plus a and y minus z is x
then
the resulting equation becomes x plus a
over 2 squared minus a over 2 squared is
equal to x plus a times
x
but the latter quantity is just x
squared plus a times x
therefore the quantity x plus a over 2
squared minus a over 2 squared is equal
to x squared plus ax
this equation is known as completing the
square
and therefore we have used the
difference of squares formula to
complete the square
[Music]
you